Register of the Friends' War Victims' Relief Committee records
Hoover Institution Archives
Friends' War Victims' Relief Committee records
1914-1923
XX333
Friends' War Victims' Relief Committee (London, England)
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Reports, correspondence, descriptive accounts, and meeting minutes relating to work conducted by the Friends' War Victims' Relief Committee during World War I and in its aftermath. Includes documentation of Quaker relief and rebuilding efforts in France, Germany, Austria, Holland, Hungary, and Poland.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
The Friends' War Victims' Relief Committee was originally established by the London Yearly Meeting in 1870 to assist civilian towns damaged by the Franco-Prussian War. This Quaker relief effort is particularly notable because it established a policy of no discrimination between the sides in war. Prior to World War I, War Victims' Relief Committees were revived in Eastern Europe (1876) and in the Balkans (1912). As World War I broke out, the War Victims' Relief Committee was reestablished to undertake relief work and post-war reconstruction. The work began in the Marne district of France and expanded to include the Netherlands, Russia, Germany, Austria, and Poland. Following America's entry into the war, the American Friends Service Committee became involved with the War Victims' Relief Committee as well. The relief work of the Friends War Victims' Relief Committee was cited by Gunnar Jahn, Chairman of the Nobel Committee, as he gave the presentation speech for the 1947 Nobel Peace Prize to the Friends Service Council and the American Friends Service Committee.
Scope and Content Note
Reports, correspondence, descriptive accounts, and meeting minutes relating to work conducted by the Friends' War Victims' Relief Committee during World War I and in its aftermath. Includes documentation of Quaker relief and rebuilding efforts in France, Germany, Austria, Holland, Hungary, and Poland.
The Society of Friends War Victims Relief Committee worked throughout World War I to reduce the impact of the fighting on the civilian population, and helped both the Allied and the Central powers recover after the war was over. The Committee's work included providing food and clothing, establishing orphanages and hospitals, combating typhus and tuberculosis, encouraging agriculture and manufacturing, improving prison conditions, and rebuilding destroyed homes. The collection is arranged alphabetically by country receiving aid.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 5 series: Austria-Hungary, 1919-1921; France, 1914-1920; Germany, 1919-1923; Holland, 1915-1918; and Poland, 1916-1923. The original arrangement by country was maintained, reflecting the local nature of work done by the War Victims' Relief Committee. The files describing work done in Holland were separated from those describing Austria-Hungary, since the aid provided was different in each country. Within each series, folder titles and arrangement were imposed during processing due to the absence of a useable original order.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Society of Friends.; Friends' Emergency and War Victims' Relief Committee (London, England).; War victims.; International relief.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; World War, 1914-1918--Austria.; World War, 1914-1918--France.; World War, 1914-1918--Germany.; World War, 1914-1918--Hungary.; World War, 1914-1918--Netherlands.; World War, 1914-1918--Poland.
Related Material
Emergency and War Victims Relief Committee publications, Hoover Institution Library
Collection Contents
- Austria-Hungary, 1919-1921.; (0.2 linear feet) (Box 1: 1-6)
  Consists of correspondence, reports, and descriptive accounts of the conditions and relief work in Austria and Hungary after World War I. In addition to information about agriculture, prisons, clothing distribution and hospitals, includes detailed descriptions of the plight of hungry Viennese children and students.
  Arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Descriptive accounts, 1920 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Descriptive accounts, 1921 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Descriptive accounts, undated (Folder 1: 4)
  - Reports, 1919-1920 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Reports, 1920-1921 (Folder 1: 6)
- France, 1914-1920.; (0.4 linear feet) (Box 1: 7 - 2: 5)
  Contains reports, correspondence, descriptive accounts, and meeting minutes. Comprises the bulk of the collection, including detailed reports of work accomplished. Depicts civilian life in the Marne district and along the Western Front, and documents medical, agricultural, manufacturing, and food assistance.
  - Articles and descriptive accounts, 1915-1919 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Correspondence, 1914-1918 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Minutes, 1915-1917 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Minutes, 1918-1920 (Folder 1: 10)
  - General reports, 1914-1915 (Folder 1: 11)
  - General reports, 1915 (Folder 1: 12)
  - General reports, 1916-1918 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Agricultural reports, 1915-1918 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Agricultural reports, 1918-1919 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Building reports, 1916-1918 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Manufacturing reports, 1918 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Medical reports, 1916-1918 (Folder 2: 5)
- Germany, 1919-1923.; (0.1 linear feet) (Box 2: 6-9)
  Includes correspondence, reports, and descriptive accounts of postwar conditions in Germany. Focuses on starvation conditions, tuberculosis, and education. Discusses devaluation of the German currency.
  - Correspondence, 1919-1921 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Descriptive accounts and reports, 1919-1920 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Descriptive accounts and reports, 1921-1923 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Descriptive accounts and reports, undated (Folder 2: 9)
- Holland, 1915-1918.; (0.02 linear feet) (Folder 2: 10)
  Reports documenting conditions in Holland for Belgian refugees during the war. Describes camp organization and providing work for the refugees.
  - Reports, 1915-1918 (Folder 2: 10)
- Poland, 1916-1923.; (0.08 linear feet) (Box 2: 11-14)
  Correspondence, reports, and descriptive accounts discussing reconstructing agriculture and homes, food programs, and preventing typhus. Also includes brief descriptions of relief work in East Galicia, West Ukraine, and Serbia.
  - Correspondence, 1919-1923 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Descriptive accounts, 1918-1923 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Descriptive accounts, undated (Folder 2: 13)
  - Reports, 1916-1920 (Folder 2: 14)